<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>m4ktub</title>
  
  <subtitle>Because some things need to be written.</subtitle>
  <link href="http://m4ktub.ws/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  
  <link href="http://m4ktub.ws/"/>
  <updated>2021-06-05T00:25:47.747Z</updated>
  <id>http://m4ktub.ws/</id>
  
  <author>
    <name>Cláudio Gil</name>
    
  </author>
  
  <generator uri="https://hexo.io/">Hexo</generator>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Most People Are Good</title>
    <link href="http://m4ktub.ws/posts/2021/06/04/most-people-are-good/"/>
    <id>http://m4ktub.ws/posts/2021/06/04/most-people-are-good/</id>
    <published>2021-06-04T01:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2021-06-05T00:25:47.747Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Regarding the COVID pandemic I’ve had no illusion that my way of approaching it and seeing the work is, maybe due to temperament, a minority view. So I’m often speaking to the wind, and the few that may stop to listen about how the unquestioning support of government restrictions is dangerous. It enables a system that allows for further restrictions, down the line, that will be difficult to stop. The ground has already been ceded. I know, I know, the slippery slope fallacy is a tempting device, and no one knows the future, but the way I see it is that I’m just describing human nature. Human nature, although not a precise clockwork mechanism, through the lens of history and personal experience, does have some predictability.</p><p>If you point at a river and predict that most water will flow to the sea you might be wrong; it may end up in a lake. But you would not be considered a fringe person because there’s a familiar pattern to rivers. People have an intuition about the nature of rivers, that water flows, that rivers usually end in the sea… No one claims to have invented psychohistory, just that there’s some predictability to people, specially in groups where they cancel and check each other’s differences. But when you point to the probable outcome of this amount of compliance people react as if they’re of a difference species. As if I was talking about a society of cats of which they had absolutely no intuition. It’s very strange. But I ramble…</p><p>When I talk to people about the dangers of allowing health passports as an accepted norm for mobility I notice people’s expressions. It’s an expression that tells how unlikely the scenario I present is to them. It’s in crazy conspiracy theory territory. The territory of evil lizard people conspiring in smoke filled rooms and whiskey glasses. But that’s not true and I often tell them, as a way to also reminding myself, that everything I predict is possible even if everyone involved is fundamentally a good person trying to do the best they can. Is just that, in a world shaped by incentives, the systems in place can make sociopaths of good people.</p><p>I do believe that most people want to do good. Be a good father, be a good mother, a good son, a good anything. But life makes you choose and form priorities. More, those priorities are shaped by what other value, like status, so you get a network of effects that transcends even the most individualistic. What is good and not good is not defined alone, no man is an island as the saying goes… Add other instincts like group conformity, risk aversion, selfishness, etc and “being a good person” often comes into conflict with self-preservation and basic drives. Now, even if people are good, they are not immune to conflict and difficult decisions… So it’s common to say one thing and do another. What people say is directed to other people, but what they do is self-serving. Actions are truer than words. This simple model, to look at actions instead of words, to look at consequences instead of intentions, to look at how the world is instead of how we think it is, is already a powerful tool to predict what comes next. And it’s accessible to anyone.</p><p>Most decisions can be understood from this prism, be it from politicians or any other person. Unfortunately, given the current system, a few people’s decisions can have an impact in millions of other people. This also means that if evil reaches that position a lot of wrong things can happen with no consequences. A lot of good people and still… a lot of wrong things happening.</p><p>Back to COVID, a doctor has no time to go through every new paper that’s released so it follows the hospital’s protocol. The director, having many people under their responsibility, has a reluctance to take risks. So it adopts some authority’s guidelines. A responsible, at that authority, faces a similar choice. If they don’t play it safe they may be held liable for some harm, so they go out of their way to add rules because better safe than sorry. And when facing a new thing, it’s safer to do what other people do than to break new ground. It’s all very natural but the higher up you got the easier it is to corrupt one person and make everyone pathological. It’s not hard to understand, it’s just unfortunate that, in many cases, people are not made responsible for the consequences of their actions.</p><p>Most people are good but add wrong incentives, moral hazard, or scarcity in general and certain behaviors emerge. Give someone the opportunity to make a fortune from vaccines and they’ll be extremely motivated to suppress alternative treatments. It’s not certain that they will but it means that at every turn the possibility will present itself as attractive. Add a number of people and you get a river, flowing in predictable directions.</p>]]></content>
    
    
      
      
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Regarding the COVID pandemic I’ve had no illusion that my way of approaching it and seeing the work is, maybe due to temperament, a minor</summary>
      
    
    
    
    <category term="opinions" scheme="http://m4ktub.ws/categories/opinions/"/>
    
    
    <category term="people" scheme="http://m4ktub.ws/tags/people/"/>
    
    <category term="nature" scheme="http://m4ktub.ws/tags/nature/"/>
    
    <category term="optimism" scheme="http://m4ktub.ws/tags/optimism/"/>
    
    <category term="conspiracies" scheme="http://m4ktub.ws/tags/conspiracies/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>The EU Digital Green Certificate</title>
    <link href="http://m4ktub.ws/posts/2021/04/03/the-eu-digital-green-certificate/"/>
    <id>http://m4ktub.ws/posts/2021/04/03/the-eu-digital-green-certificate/</id>
    <published>2021-04-03T01:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2021-04-14T01:00:00.000Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Excelentíssimo Senhor Primeiro Ministro<br>Dr. António Costa</p><p>Venho pedir-lhe que reconsidere a estratégia atual do governo em relação ao Certificado Verde Digital COVID-19 que está a ser considerado (<a href="https://ec.europa.eu/info/live-work-travel-eu/coronavirus-response/safe-covid-19-vaccines-europeans/covid-19-digital-green-certificates_pt">1</a>) e propor-lhe alternativas.</p><p>Já em fevereiro mencionou o Certificado Verde (<a href="https://www.tsf.pt/mundo/falta-de-dados-cientificos-esta-a-condicionar-certificado-verde-13396061.html">2</a>), que descreveu como um documento não identificado que permitirá uma maior facilidade de circulação na UE ao evitar medidas de quarentena. Nessa mesma altura reconheceu a tentação para ver esse documento como um “passaporte sanitário” e pediu que se evitasse o termo. Vários protestos contra este ou mecanismos semelhantes tornam evidente que essa é uma interpretação comum. Apesar do mecanismo proposto pelo governo de Israel ser diferente, o protesto ocorrido em Tel Aviv (<a href="https://www.jpost.com/israel-news/protesters-demonstrate-against-vaccine-coercion-green-passports-in-tel-aviv-660106">3</a>) é possivelmente o mais indicativo da reação popular a um “passaporte sanitário”.</p><p>Compreendo o desejo de recuperar a atividade turística em Portugal, e livre circulação em geral, de uma forma segura. O Certificado Verde, como método, reafirma a eficácia do plano de vacinação ao mesmo tempo que evita a necessidade de uma coordenação estreita entre estados. Sem uma identificação pessoal, como mencionado, este Certificado poderia ser visto como um mecanismo de <em>fast track</em>, algo já popular em todos os aeroportos. </p><p>Existem, no entanto, diferenças substanciais entre o Certificado Verde e o que poderia ser um bilhete com opção para <em>fast track</em>. A posse do certificado não identifica apenas o acesso a um serviço mas um aspeto pessoal de saúde. O mecanismo anunciado já assume que cada certificado será pessoalmente identificado e que essa informação será partilhada para, entre outras coisas, impedir a transmissibilidade de certificados. Isto significa que os portugueses terão que escolher entre encargos onerosos, ao viajar para outro país, ou comunicar aspetos privados da saúde a terceiros com os quais não detém qualquer relação. Sendo os encargos controlados pelo país de destino é possível construir incentivos poderosos à utilização do Certificado Verde tornando a opcionalidade do esquema ilusória, do ponto de vista prático.</p><p>O sucesso, insucesso e evolução destes mecanismos são ditados por esquemas de incentivos. Uma vez introduzido o Certificado Verde, os incentivos são para a sua expansão como sistema de controlo de imigração e ferramenta para futuras pandemias. Se Certificado Verde é útil agora, dita a razão que poderá ser útil no futuro e é mais simples manter o mecanismo. Um conjunto de incentivos semelhantes levaram ao estabelecimento da norma internacional de passaportes que conhecemos e continua a ser expandida, pelo que existem precedentes. Neste contexto, a expressão “passaporte sanitário” não é apenas um rótulo pejorativo, mas uma descrição do aspeto que este mecanismo de Certificado Verde tem, para muitas pessoas, num horizonte próximo. Para além disso, a urgência da sua introdução (planeado até agosto) não permite a transparência e discussão que imperariam levando ao aumento espectável do nível de ceticismo.</p><p>A implementação deste mecanismo poderá ter repercussões políticas imprevisíveis uma vez que assenta na interpretação deste mecanismo por parte da opinião pública. Cada país é responsável pelas restrições que coloca sobre turistas e imigrantes. Do ponto de vista de Portugal é razoável argumentar que é possível aceitar turismo e imigração sem necessidade de um mecanismo como o Certificado Verde, quarentenas ou isolamentos. Este tipo de abertura pode ser alvo de críticas, mas essas críticas são locais e mais simples de endereçar tendo em conta o plano de vacinação em curso, o ano de conhecimento acumulado sobre a pandemia e a crescente tensão entre medidas restritivas e as mais variadas emergências pessoais que se acumulam.</p><p>É conhecido que a COVID-19 é uma infeção sazonal com bastante menos incidência no Verão (<a href="https://www.euromomo.eu/graphs-and-maps/">4</a>). Sabe-se também que o vírus afeta de forma grave pessoas mais idosas ou com outras patologias associadas (<a href="https://covid19.min-saude.pt/wp-content/uploads/2021/04/408_DGS_boletim_20210414.pdf">5</a>). Atualmente estima-se completar uma maioria do plano de vacinação até ao final do Verão. Mesmo com o atraso espectável deste plano de vacinação, a maioria das pessoas consideradas vulneráveis estarão vacinadas ou terão tido acesso a vacina. É também inegável que todos os portugueses estão cientes da pandemia e ajustaram os seus comportamentos. Existem também planos preventivos como Clean &amp; Safe (<a href="https://portugalcleanandsafe.com/en">6</a>) que têm o apoio do governo de Portugal. Este programa, lançado em abril de 2020, foi considerado seguro para turistas e portugueses por associações de hotéis e Turismo de Portugal, pelo que não há motivo para o considerar inseguro agora.</p><p>Por tudo o indicado, seria possível comunicar a abertura segura de fronteiras terrestes e aéreas de forma compreensível ao público. Esta ação demonstraria controlo da situação, seguiria as recomendações internacionais, afirmaria direitos humanos, compromisso por valores fundamentais Europeus e seria bem recebida por vários sectores da sociedade. O Certificado Verde, mesmo não sendo necessário, pode continuar a ser discutido num horizonte temporal mais alargado aliviando a apreensão sentida por pessoas em toda a Europa.</p><p>Agradeço a atenção dispensada e espero que, com esta exposição, considere o seu posicionamento face à promoção do Certificado Verde no horizonte temporal previsto.</p><p>Sem outro assunto, despeço-me com um desejo de saúde, prosperidade e os meus sinceros cumprimentos.</p><p>Cláudio Gil<br>Português</p>]]></content>
    
    
      
      
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Excelentíssimo Senhor Primeiro Ministro&lt;br&gt;Dr. António Costa&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Venho pedir-lhe que reconsidere a estratégia atual do governo em rela</summary>
      
    
    
    
    <category term="opinions" scheme="http://m4ktub.ws/categories/opinions/"/>
    
    
    <category term="pandemic" scheme="http://m4ktub.ws/tags/pandemic/"/>
    
    <category term="covid" scheme="http://m4ktub.ws/tags/covid/"/>
    
    <category term="eu" scheme="http://m4ktub.ws/tags/eu/"/>
    
    <category term="passport" scheme="http://m4ktub.ws/tags/passport/"/>
    
    <category term="freedom" scheme="http://m4ktub.ws/tags/freedom/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>The Heroes That Do Nothing</title>
    <link href="http://m4ktub.ws/posts/2020/12/17/the-heroes-that-do-nothing/"/>
    <id>http://m4ktub.ws/posts/2020/12/17/the-heroes-that-do-nothing/</id>
    <published>2020-12-17T00:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2021-04-02T01:00:00.000Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If 2020 teached me anything was that ideologies that make people feel good for doing absolutely nothing are a thing. </p><p>A lot as been said about the pandemic but one aspect that I haven’t seen explored is how the virtue signaling economy was capitalized by governments to achieve lockdown acceptance. when I say “virtue signaling economy” I’m referring to the use of “feel good” labels, phrases, and symbols that started to be attached to products. Labels like “bio”, “green”, “eco”, “organic”, “sustainable” allow companies to charge a premium because clients get the product AND the feeling of contributing to something noble. Why buy a book and donate to the poor when you can buy a book that says in the cover “1€ goes to the poor”. You’re just saving one step while still being able to say, with a clean conscience, I’m helping the poor. Right?</p><p>Most people have noticed this pattern but maybe, like I did, dismissed it as innocuous foolishness. In hindesight, the receptiveness to that strategy was actually showing there was a void and that people were filling it. A desire for noble causes and meaning. Maybe in such a international world, local daily life seems insignificant and these products provide a way to amplify a local action and have an impact at the international stage. I drink ethically grown coffee and that’s like helping farmers half a world away. I use paper straws and save the oceans. Doing this things make me a good person automatically. </p><p>Obviously, that appetite is the perfect opportunity for abuse or exploitation because it’s mostly based on virtue signaling. As long as you can generate the feeling of moral superiority without requiring to much inconvenience you can sell something. Either a product or an idea. If additionally your action is visible and can be appreciated by other people even better.</p><p>I believe that was an important factor in getting acceptance for lockdowns, as a way to fight the pandemic. The underlying idea is pretty simple: stay home and avoid contagion. It’s true enough, without people to spread to, the virus cannot propagate. But there was a twist in that it was framed differently. The initial slogan was “flatten the curve” which has the same characteristics as other virtue signaling labels. It allows you to hide your defects under the guise that you’re protecting others. It promises to amplify your actions. And it requires no effort (if you can actually stay home). Basically, you can be an hero and help save lives by staying home binge-watching Netflix. What a bargain!</p><p>I’m not ignoring there’s a kernel of truth to all these things. That’s part of their attractiveness. Like a good lie. If Starbucks really does avoid sourcing coffee form exploitative farmers then by preferring Starbucks, instead of other brand that does not, you are contributing to a world where no coffee farmer is exploitative. The issue is that there’s an unappreciated difference between being a good person and thinking you are good person. You can convince someone they are being good (or bad) while they are not. An obvious example is war propaganda, were people are convinced that killing otherwise peaceful strangers is the right thing to do. Even if conflict is innevitable, and you’re acting to prevent harm on yourself or others, it’s not always obvious if actual harm exists in any other place than your head.</p><p>In a virtue signaling economy the focus is on the demonstration of virtue, that is, the local action and what it means. There are huge incentives to create new “feel good “ narratives and disregard their connection with the real world or outwright misrepresent those connections. After a major hurricane that are many campaigns asking for donations to help the people affected by the disaster. You donate and feel good about it. If you later find that the money never reached the area most people will not think “I did not do the right thing” but instead will think “corrupt people took advantage of me”. To the good feeling of donating then you add what is now the good feeling of being a victim. A two hit combo of virtuosity with zero of the intended results.</p><p>This cultural shift is here to stay for a little while longer and it helped accept lockdowns. If the narrative ever changes to “lockdowns were catastrophic” people will think they did the right thing and polititions are to only ones to blame. Never will it occur, to most people, that supporting the wrong thing is also the wrong thing, even if you’re convinced of the contrary. </p>]]></content>
    
    
      
      
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;If 2020 teached me anything was that ideologies that make people feel good for doing absolutely nothing are a thing. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lot as bee</summary>
      
    
    
    
    <category term="ideas" scheme="http://m4ktub.ws/categories/ideas/"/>
    
    
    <category term="ideology" scheme="http://m4ktub.ws/tags/ideology/"/>
    
    <category term="virtue" scheme="http://m4ktub.ws/tags/virtue/"/>
    
    <category term="signaling" scheme="http://m4ktub.ws/tags/signaling/"/>
    
    <category term="ethics" scheme="http://m4ktub.ws/tags/ethics/"/>
    
    <category term="pandemic" scheme="http://m4ktub.ws/tags/pandemic/"/>
    
    <category term="covid" scheme="http://m4ktub.ws/tags/covid/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>The Mythical Community and the Permissionless of Bitcoin Cash</title>
    <link href="http://m4ktub.ws/posts/2020/09/09/the-mythical-community-of-bitcoin-cash/"/>
    <id>http://m4ktub.ws/posts/2020/09/09/the-mythical-community-of-bitcoin-cash/</id>
    <published>2020-09-09T01:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2021-07-01T21:40:18.366Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is the Marrakech market in the morning, with a close up of the underlying technology that powers it, Jemma el-Fnaa.</p><img src="/posts/2020/09/09/the-mythical-community-of-bitcoin-cash/jemaa-el-fnaa1.jpg" class="" title="Jemaa el-Fnaa in the morning"><p>This, however, is the Marrakech market in the evening. Exactly the same underlying technology but filled with people coming together to exchange goods and services. Even ignoring the warm evening tones, it’s evident there’s a much more vibrant and rich atmosphere. It’s full of life.</p><img src="/posts/2020/09/09/the-mythical-community-of-bitcoin-cash/jemaa-el-fnaa2.jpg" class="" title="Jemaa el-Fnaa in the evening"><p>So what exactly is the Marrakech market? It certainly exists, since it’s internationally famous, described in several guides, and I’m writing about it. But it’s not only the public square. Nor is it a specific group of people, since those change every day. The market is all of those things together, a pattern of behaviors around Jemaa el-Fnaa that changes constantly but that still keeps some recognizable purpose and consistency over time. Could the Marrakech market be moved to another space outside of the medina? Hardly. It’s certainly possible to move all the people, tents, and behaviors to that new place. People may even call it the Marrakech market but there would always be a new and old market. Jemaa el-Fnaa, inert as it is without the people, is an essential part of the market’s identity.</p><h2 id="The-Bitcoin-Cash-Community"><a href="#The-Bitcoin-Cash-Community" class="headerlink" title="The Bitcoin Cash Community"></a>The Bitcoin Cash Community</h2><p>What has any of this to do with Bitcoin Cash?</p><p>It’s easier to talk about a concrete and recognizable thing but both share enough important characteristics to talk about communities. The underlying technology is inert and worthless without the people that value what it provides. People can enter, leave, and participate. And in both there are specialized groups of people, that band together in certain corners. This allows to talk about the Bitcoin Cash community by comparison.</p><p>Several people have been talking about what the Bitcoin Cash community wants, what it decided, that some decisions are its prerogative, what it rejects or accepts, all sort of things. But if we use the Marrakech market as example, would those statements even make sense. Can the market want something? Off course not. Spice merchants in the spice souk could all be in agreement that the market needs something to block the evening wind but if they announced “the market has decided to install some panels at the entry of the market” they would be laughed at and ignored.</p><p>Spice merchants may be important and well established Marrakesh merchants. Their local status could carry weight and influence other merchants to agree but it’s ridiculous for a person, or even all merchants of a souk, to claim to represent the entire Marrakesh market.</p><p>Consider an every day person that frequently goes to the market to buy vegetables and cloths. Even if that person is comfortably at home, there’s an expectation that she can go to the market tomorrow evening and find everything she needs. The Marrakesh market’s community includes her and everyone like her because their collective behaviors is what makes merchants gather there at around the same time. We could argue the extent, but even tourists abroad share some membership in the Marrakesh market. They may decide to finally go there, after seeing the travel brochure for the hundredth time, and they have a certain expectation of what they’ll find.</p><h2 id="Size-and-borders"><a href="#Size-and-borders" class="headerlink" title="Size and borders"></a>Size and borders</h2><p>The Marakech market has no precise border that you can trace. There’s no way to know who’s inside and who’s outside. Without that border, there’s no way to speak for all its members.</p><p>The common answer to this criticism that, although we can identify this amorphous group of people it’s meaningless to speak in its name, is that this might be true when Bitcoin Cash becomes world money but it’s not true now because we’re so few people. There’s clearly a community since we almost feel we could name every one. We can also come together share opinions, come to agreement, and then speak with confidence that most think the same. As if the Marrakesh market currently had only the builders quarter.</p><p>The main issue, though, is that you can’t have a concrete community, with the characteristics people ascribe to the Bitcoin Cash community, without the border. Without a way to control who comes in. Without a way to say “we abide by these rules and if you want to join so must you”. We can’t count the people we don’t know even exist and they all form their own expectations about Bitcoin Cash. Clearly there are people that are more influential than others, the so called opinion leaders, but no opinion leader was appointed or elected so it makes no sense to speak for the “silent majority”.</p><img src="/posts/2020/09/09/the-mythical-community-of-bitcoin-cash/lx-electric.jpg" class="" title="Bica elevator, Lisbon"><p>Imagine you take the same bus to work for years. It’s a small bus, 20 people capacity. You’re used to see some people. Neighbors, people that enter two stops after, people that enter when you’re about to leave. There’s a sense of familiarity. You even know the driver’s kids and ask how they’re doing… Is this a community? It’s not because all sort of strangers also enter and leave the bus. You have no way to say “we’ve decided 15 people are enough and you can’t enter” to someone at a stop.</p><p>Bitcoin Cash is a permissionless network making it impossible to create a border, like we could with a physical place. It’s a totally unsuitable technology to form a unified community. Like cash. It’s forever permeable to foreign elements and dissidents that can never be spoken for. As it should. Like the Marrakech market, the Bitcoin Cash community exists in the totality of people’s expectations and behaviors over time. Although some characterizations can be made, like “its paranoid” or “aims for p2p cash for the world”, no specific action or opinion can be claimed to represent the entire community.</p><p>It is true that opinion makers, in a small network, can hold more sway on the opinions of users. If their opinion changes, it’s easier for a greater portion of the users to follow. It’s also true that builders, in a small network, can raise in status more quickly. If you’re competent and the competition scarce then you’re skills are quickly recognized and highly valued. But to say this is how it should be is to want the network small. To want your opinion dominate other opinions is to want the network closed.</p><p>That’s the main danger I see with this collectivist mentality. The sense of belonging, unified goals, and common action requires borders and checkpoints. It requires the network to be permissioned. If the idea of having it gated now and opened in the future could even work, to foster a more healthy culture in its infancy, it would still require a shift that is uncertain and unnecessary. Instead, we can just start treating the Bitcoin Cash community as it already is and will always be: full of different people that cannot be expelled or stopped from doing what they want. Seeing it like this, forces us to find sustainable solutions to foster the desired culture of celebrating permissionless p2p cash. It forces us to look forward and outward, towards global adoption, without conflict as the first option for conformity.</p><p>Let’s keep Bitcoin Cash permissionless, shall we?</p>]]></content>
    
    
      
      
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is the Marrakech market in the morning, with a close up of the underlying technology that powers it, Jemma el-Fnaa.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/p</summary>
      
    
    
    
    <category term="ideas" scheme="http://m4ktub.ws/categories/ideas/"/>
    
    
    <category term="bitcoin" scheme="http://m4ktub.ws/tags/bitcoin/"/>
    
    <category term="community" scheme="http://m4ktub.ws/tags/community/"/>
    
    <category term="markets" scheme="http://m4ktub.ws/tags/markets/"/>
    
    <category term="permissionless" scheme="http://m4ktub.ws/tags/permissionless/"/>
    
    <category term="collectivism" scheme="http://m4ktub.ws/tags/collectivism/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>The Bitcoin Cash Room</title>
    <link href="http://m4ktub.ws/posts/2020/05/01/the-bitcoin-cash-room/"/>
    <id>http://m4ktub.ws/posts/2020/05/01/the-bitcoin-cash-room/</id>
    <published>2020-05-01T01:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2020-10-03T01:00:00.000Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>2020-06-29</strong><strong>WARNING</strong>: The SSB Bitcoin Cash Room was decommissioned due to lack of participation from the community. Being decentralized, anyone using SSB is still accessible through other rooms, pubs, or directly. If interested, just ask around.</p><hr><p>Who wants to try (yet) another social network?</p><p>Here me out.</p><p>The next step for Bitcoin Cash development is one of unprecedented collaboration. One of the things that enables collaboration is a a social platform for open participation and discussion. There’s no shortage of social platforms like <insert names of social platforms here until you feel tired> but I’ve been monitoring <a href="https://scuttlebutt.nz/">Scuttlebutt</a> and I think it fits the culture of the Bitcoin Cash development and wider communities very well.</p><p>Anyone can join. You just need an app. But it obviously helps - being a social network and all - if you can also find another person.</p><ul><li><strong>It’s peer-to-peer.</strong> You can exchange messages via Bluetooth or Wi-Fi directly.</li><li><strong>You can’t be banned.</strong> At most you can block people or be blocked but that does not affect anyone else. Everyone following you will see your messages the same.</li><li><strong>No content can be censored.</strong> All messages are stored in your and your followers’ devices. As long as someone is available your messages are available.</li><li><strong>No blockchain is hurt in the process.</strong> Although messages are public and immutable that is achieved the “normal” way. No proof-of-work is required.</li></ul><h2 id="A-meeting-place"><a href="#A-meeting-place" class="headerlink" title="A meeting place"></a>A meeting place</h2><p>A common “problem” with these kind of networks, for very distributed communities, is how to find other people. You just can’t connect to others directly through the Internet so you need some kind of meeting place.</p><p>For that reason I’ve setup <a href="https://bch-room.m4ktub.ws/">the Bitcoin Cash Room</a>. It simply allows people that connect to it to find other people and exchange messages.</p><p>To connect to room just copy and paste the following invite code into <a href="https://www.manyver.se/">Manyverse</a> or <a href="https://github.com/ssbc/patchwork/releases">Patchwork</a>. This invite code and a QR code is also available at <a href="https://scuttlebutt.nz/">the room’s landing page</a>.</p><p><strong>EDIT</strong>: You might not be able to see other people in the room, if you use Patchwork. Click on the room and follow it. It will not follow you back, as the Pub, but if everyone does that then you can discover people the same.</p><pre><code>net:bch-room.m4ktub.ws:8008~shs:8eyMoHDDGcbxHPc8tUs971k59LZyBoHqwNyJvNwnVAc=:SSB+Room+PSK3TLYC2T86EHQCUHBUHASCASE18JBV24=</code></pre><p>With a Scuttlebutt room the server never stores any of the messages. This is the more private option but it also means people need to be online at the same time. Remember that you and your followers are the ones that store your messages so you and another follower need to be online for her to get your messages. Then, either you or that follower can be online for another follower to get your messages. And so on.</p><h2 id="Your-friendly-bartender"><a href="#Your-friendly-bartender" class="headerlink" title="Your friendly bartender"></a>Your friendly bartender</h2><p>Although rooms are a great addition to Scuttlebutt it does make it harder to bootstrap the relations initially. Specially if people are in different time zones, which they are. It also diminishes the user experience somewhat because, when you finally have the time to check what’s new, you might actually miss everyone that might have new messages for you.</p><p>To help with that, I’ve also setup what in Scuttlebutt is called a Pub. Like your local pub, it’s the place for all the gossip to spread. It achieves that because the “bartender” will always be your friend (follow you back) when you join the pub. That means it will get and store all your new messages when you connect and also give you new messages from the people you follow.</p><p>Obviously, in this case, the Pub (or the bartender) stores all the messages from its friends. Although the Scuttlebutt network is public, in the sense that anyone can see your feed, the more privacy oriented people might want to avoid the Pub sine that reduces the exposure somewhat. The plan is to close the Pub once a network of people is formed as it should no longer be needed.</p><p>As with the Room, to connect to the Pub just copy and paste the following invite code into <a href="https://www.manyver.se/">Manyverse</a> or <a href="https://github.com/ssbc/patchwork/releases">Patchwork</a>. You will then be able to see all the Pub’s friends and follow them regardless if they are online or not.</p><pre><code>bch-room.m4ktub.ws:9008:@bja5QOu5uqT/MC8udTZbE21fI+L0R2KH0QDJRTHwkYM=.ed25519~UKrMEEE+S6rSEUyefJjz5fc3yj271ldNtd3bQKXK+yc=</code></pre><h2 id="Invitation"><a href="#Invitation" class="headerlink" title="Invitation"></a>Invitation</h2><p>The most popular platforms and channels are not doing any favors to themselves by filtering information and banning people with dissident opinions.</p><p>Let’s join? What about just trying new thing?</p><p>The future will be person-to-person!</p>]]></content>
    
    
      
      
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2020-06-29&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;WARNING&lt;/strong&gt;: The SSB Bitcoin Cash Room was decommissioned due to lack of participation from the </summary>
      
    
    
    
    <category term="projects" scheme="http://m4ktub.ws/categories/projects/"/>
    
    
    <category term="bitcoin" scheme="http://m4ktub.ws/tags/bitcoin/"/>
    
    <category term="scuttlebutt" scheme="http://m4ktub.ws/tags/scuttlebutt/"/>
    
    <category term="manyverse" scheme="http://m4ktub.ws/tags/manyverse/"/>
    
    <category term="patchwork" scheme="http://m4ktub.ws/tags/patchwork/"/>
    
    <category term="collaboration" scheme="http://m4ktub.ws/tags/collaboration/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Revisiting Ownership in Bitcoin</title>
    <link href="http://m4ktub.ws/posts/2020/02/08/revisiting-ownership-in-bitcoin/"/>
    <id>http://m4ktub.ws/posts/2020/02/08/revisiting-ownership-in-bitcoin/</id>
    <published>2020-02-08T00:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2020-05-01T10:49:28.642Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<img src="/posts/2020/02/08/revisiting-ownership-in-bitcoin/monkey-thinking.jpg" class="" title="Photograph by Juan Rumimpunu on Unsplash"><p><em><a href="https://unsplash.com/photos/nLXOatvTaLo">Photograph</a> by <a href="https://unsplash.com/@earbiscuits">Juan Rumimpunu</a> on <a href="https://unsplash.com/">Unsplash</a>.</em></p><p>People like <a href="https://twitter.com/vinarmani">@vinarmani</a>, and more recently <a href="https://twitter.com/DustinDry1st">@DustinDry1st</a>, have defended the notion that you cannot own bitcoins [<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Jh7BTOPh5qM">3</a>], [<a href="https://medium.com/@dustindreifuerst/the-principles-of-bitcoin-2c69ad339ea">4</a>]. This is met with resistance since it goes against a popular notion of ownership in Bitcoin, and a tradition that goes back to Satoshi Nakamoto and the <a href="https://bitcoin.org/bitcoin.pdf">whitepaper</a>.</p><p>I have already written a <a href="/posts/2018/12/22/bitcoin-cash-101-ownership/">post</a> describing the concept of ownership in Bitcoin. I want to defend this tradition again by showing that the particular reasoning done by Vin Armani and Dustin Dreifuerst is invalid and by arguing that, in their argument, they ignore that language, as a consensus mechanism, depends very much on the context.</p><p>I’ll start with the logic part.</p><h2 id="A-hidden-assumption"><a href="#A-hidden-assumption" class="headerlink" title="A hidden assumption"></a>A hidden assumption</h2><p>The reasoning, supporting their conclusion that you can’t own bitcoins, is made in a slightly different ways. Put simply, they argue that if something is made of parts and you can’t claim something on any of the parts then you also cannot claim that something on the whole. More specifically:</p><p>Vin said “If you can’t own UTXOs and you can’t own private keys, you can’t own bitcoins”.Dustin said, In relation to private keys, “no matter how many digits you affix to it, you have no more ownership of it than a reduction of that number to anyone or more parts”.</p><p>This reasoning has an underlying assumption that is not proven and therefore, even if the conclusion ends up being true, the reasoning is invalid. You cannot conclude the latter from the former because it is not sufficient. Later I will also argue that the conclusion is not true at all and why.</p><p>The underlying assumption, in the presented reasoning, is that the whole is in the same class as the parts and therefore that any property that is valid for the part is also valid for the whole and vice-versa. Intuitively we can think of “class” as a name for a group of things sharing the same properties like “numbers”, of which 1 is a particular element.</p><p>To avoid getting too abstract let’s explore some examples.</p><h3 id="Simple-examples"><a href="#Simple-examples" class="headerlink" title="Simple examples"></a>Simple examples</h3><p>The simplest way to show what this means is to provide examples for both valid and invalid arguments.</p><p>A valid argument, in the same form, could be something like “if 2 is even and 4 is even then 2+4 is even”.</p><p>Proving mathematically that 6 is even is beyond the point. What’s required here is to know that “parity” is a property of “integers”, that adding two even numbers results in an even number, and that all 2, 4 and 6 are “integers”. In this example, it makes perfect sense to talk about the parity of 6 in relation to 2 and 4 because it is in the same “class” of 2 and 4.</p><p>An invalid argument would be something like “if 2 is even and 4 is even then the point (2, 4) is even”. </p><p>In this example we can see that (2, 4), interpreted as the representation of a point in a graph, is not in the same “integers” class as 2 and 4. As a “point” it’s not even correct to talk about its “parity” because points have no such property. With this example we can see that just by combining the parts differently we produced something of a “different” class.</p><p>Vin Armani, for example, needs to assume that combining the exclusive knowledge of a private key with the public Bitcoin ledger produces nothing more than another “number”. If that was the case then he could simply have said that you can’t own a number. If that’s not the case then the argument is invalid. </p><p>You just need to consider that this combination of parts could produce something different to allow the possibility that ownership is a valid aspect of it. The same way you can consider that a combination of ingredients produces something different, like a meal, and not just another ingredient. </p><h3 id="A-more-visual-example"><a href="#A-more-visual-example" class="headerlink" title="A more visual example"></a>A more visual example</h3><p>I think Dustin’s formulation requires a different kind of example because, in his post, it is clear that if you’re just adding numbers then the result is still a number, that is, it is in the same class.</p><p>To keep with a theme close to the the original argument, consider the encryption of a message. We don’t need to know details of encryption but only that you also have a private key and there’s a mechanism that takes the private key and a message to produce an encrypted message.</p><img src="/posts/2020/02/08/revisiting-ownership-in-bitcoin/encryption-mechanism.png" class=""><p>The encrypted message can only be read by someone that has the private key or someone with a powerful enough computer to “break” the encryption, that is, try a lot of keys until they find one that works.</p><p>Given that, you can ask “is the encryption secure, that is, can I send the encrypted message over the Internet, for anyone to see, and be relatively sure that no-one will be able to ‘break’ it in the next 10 years”?  What you find is that answering that question depends on the size of the key.</p><img src="/posts/2020/02/08/revisiting-ownership-in-bitcoin/years-to-break-key-size.png" class=""><p>A small key is in the class of “insecure keys”. A large key, above a certain level, is called secure or, in other words, is in the class of “secure keys”. In this example, encryption keys are still just numbers but, when combined with an encryption mechanism, they become of a different quality as their size grows. Adding one more digit may be the difference between a secure key and an insecure key. This means Dustin’s argument also fails to account for this possible transition. If the argument is restricted to the math domain then speaking about ownership is meaningless anyway, as that concept does not even exist. But if the argument is made in the Bitcoin domain then you also have to show that all numbers are of the same quality, if you want to draw the conclusion that ownership of the private key is as meaningless as owning a number.</p><h2 id="The-importance-of-context"><a href="#The-importance-of-context" class="headerlink" title="The importance of context"></a>The importance of context</h2><p>Every language evolves by consensus. It’s probably the first permissionless and decentralized consensus mechanism. But the world has infinite things and we have too few words so we reuse them. A star is not only that thing in the sky but also that person in the stage. You have two legs but so can a race…</p><p>Meaning depends fundamentally on the context. Since what separates a context from another is arbitrary, people can and do develop different languages to talk about different aspects of the same thing. For example, when talking about perfumes you can identify a rose by “C6H12O2”, the language of chemistry, or by smelling a “pleasant floral or fruity rose aroma”, the language of fragrances.</p><p>What is important here, is that although both languages are valid they are most useful when communicating within their specific context. There’s nothing “fruity” about either geranyl acetate or a rose but the meaning of “fruity” is well defined in the slang of fragrances. To connect with the previous examples, and go back to the main point, saying that an acetate is “fruity” is as nonsensical as saying a point in a graph is even. You can’t just take a word out of context and assume it will have the same meaning.</p><h3 id="The-language-of-Bitcoin"><a href="#The-language-of-Bitcoin" class="headerlink" title="The language of Bitcoin"></a>The language of Bitcoin</h3><p>The Bitcoin system is still young and is still being constantly redefined but it’s evident that we can talk about Bitcoin and there’s already a specific language for this new domain. We talk about miners, which are not not actual miners, and about a blockchain, which is neither a chain nor formed by actual blocks. Sometimes the meaning of a word changes as more people get involved. The term blockchain started with Satoshi but was already used very broadly, by a large number of people, to describe cryptocurrencies that have no resemblance to what motivated the term. Sometimes even to describe an entire industry. It now seems to be settling on a more generic version of the original meaning, as the majority of people discover other words to use, like “crypto”…</p><p>In this context, the meaning of ownership in Bitcoin was never ill defined. It comes directly from the whitepaper so it’s no wonder that the popular notion of ownership is deep-rooted. It’s simple, easy, and useful. It greatly simplifies importing other concepts, like “custodian”, into this domain because their meaning can be easily adapted. As owner of bitcoins you already know it’s your responsibility to protect them. As you transfer them to a custodian you know you’ve given up ownership but also the responsibility to secure them.</p><p>This meaning may evolve and the term “ownership” may even fall in disuse, if it proves to be too confusing or simply not useful when communicating. But the arguments presented against the possibility to “own” bitcoins don’t make the claim that the term is not useful, or provide an alternative meaning. Instead, they claim the word is meaningless, that is, that you can’t even claim ownership of a bitcoin.</p><h3 id="Crossing-domains"><a href="#Crossing-domains" class="headerlink" title="Crossing domains"></a>Crossing domains</h3><p>It’s perfectly possible to understand the sentence “not your keys, not you bitcoins” without any knowledge of the whitepaper, cryptography, or mathematics. The traditional meaning of ownership is well defined in this Bitcoin context. Therefore, and as mentioned before, it’s important to see if, in the arguments against ownership, the meaning of ownership was imported from a different context. If it was, then we might as well be using two completely different words and claiming they are the same is the confusion.</p><p>Let’s take, from <a href="https://medium.com/@dustindreifuerst/the-principles-of-bitcoin-2c69ad339ea">Dustin’s article</a>, one of the last conclusions around Bitcoin ownership:</p><blockquote><p>[…] money implies ownership with certain legal rights that in Bitcoin cannot be enforced.</p></blockquote><p>My understanding of what is meant is that Bitcoin can never achieve “money” status because you can’t claim “ownership with certain legal rights” of Bitcoin. But the “ownership” that is used here is a different concept, related with properties of fiat money. We can make a sentence like “you can own a bitcoin but you will never money-own it”, if you’re assuming you’re talking about Bitcoin. By “money-own” I’m referring to the other concept of ownership. If we’re not assuming Bitcoin, as a context, we might say the reverse “money in your hand is protected by certain legal rights of ownership while the Bitcoin notion of ownership grants no such rights”. In this last case “the Bitcoin notion of ownership” is a whole lot of words to say “ownership” if you’re in the Bitcoin context.</p><p>Dustin, while never actually being clear about this distinction, does not make the strongest case that you can’t own, in any sense, Bitcoin. The article can just be interpreted, in this sense, as claiming that if none of the historical definitions of ownership apply to Bitcoin then people should understand Bitcoin not as money but primarily as an enabler of greater individual sovereignty, from which money can emerge. It’s in Vin’s video that a stronger claim is made.</p><blockquote><p>If you can’t own UTXOs and you can’t own private keys, you can’t own bitcoins.</p></blockquote><p>Two different “ownerships” are also being used here. In this context “UTXOs” are not in the Bitcoin domain. Previously in the video Vin mentions they just numbers. If they are just numbers they are in the math domain. The private key is a term from the cryptographic domain. Vin also claims it’s just a number so we’re again talking about the math domain. But “bitcoins”, the final part, is in the Bitcoin domain and the audience is assuming that. Besides the reasoning aspect previously mentioned, ownership is being used in the math domain where it is, in fact, meaningless and that meaninglessness is being transported to the “ownership” of Bitcoin as if it was the same concept in the same context.</p><p>If we interpret UTXOs and “private keys” in the Bitcoin context, it’s indifferent that they can be decomposed into numbers. The only thing that matters is their properties in relation to people and the Bitcoin protocol. If bitcoins are to be interpreted in the math world then they are also a very long sequence of numbers and ownership becomes indeed meaningless. The problem is in bridging these worlds, taking a word from one, and speak it in the other expecting people to understand you.</p><h2 id="Conclusion"><a href="#Conclusion" class="headerlink" title="Conclusion"></a>Conclusion</h2><p>Communication is challenging and I’m a believer that it’s of primary importance to understand your audience and meet them where they are. If you speak to yourself, while it may challenge a listener to come closer to you, there can be no reasonable expectation of being understood. And the more you speak to yourself the more people misunderstand you as you create new meanings that are inaccessible.</p><p>While I’m making this criticism, I must note that I’m not challenging most arguments. Vin and Dustin’s reflection provides an important insight that may expand people’s understanding of their relationship with cryptocurrencies. More importantly it may guide people into seeking and valuing what is indeed revolutionary in this experiment. But the fact that you can’t own Bitcoin is not that insight and I believe this mutual understanding will help the exploration move forward towards a new consensus and meaning for ownership.</p>]]></content>
    
    
      
      
    <summary type="html">&lt;img src=&quot;/posts/2020/02/08/revisiting-ownership-in-bitcoin/monkey-thinking.jpg&quot; class=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;Photograph by Juan Rumimpunu on Unsplash&quot;&gt;
</summary>
      
    
    
    
    <category term="ideas" scheme="http://m4ktub.ws/categories/ideas/"/>
    
    
    <category term="bitcoin" scheme="http://m4ktub.ws/tags/bitcoin/"/>
    
    <category term="ownership" scheme="http://m4ktub.ws/tags/ownership/"/>
    
    <category term="communication" scheme="http://m4ktub.ws/tags/communication/"/>
    
    <category term="language" scheme="http://m4ktub.ws/tags/language/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Surprise! Here&#39;s Bitcoin</title>
    <link href="http://m4ktub.ws/posts/2019/03/06/surprise-heres-bitcoin/"/>
    <id>http://m4ktub.ws/posts/2019/03/06/surprise-heres-bitcoin/</id>
    <published>2019-03-06T00:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2019-11-13T12:14:29.400Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<img src="/posts/2019/03/06/surprise-heres-bitcoin/surprise-heres-bitcoin.jpg" class=""><p>I’ve been wondering about a more effective way to communicate the bitcoin concept and why does it matter. Typically I come across two kind of people.</p><ol><li>Like-minded people who feel offended for not being told about bitcoin earlier, or</li><li>The majority that tolerates me, and my unexplainable excited exposition, to various degrees.</li></ol><p>Even if people go like “Oh, that’s cool!” there’s no real incentive for them to go out of their way and try new stuff. To literally go play with money. This topic has been discussed before but typically it’s from a monetary incentive perspective where we try to get those greedy bastards to jump through all the hoops because of the discount they have. The typical case here is <a href="https://purse.io/">Purse.io</a>. The complementary approach I’m thinking is a little different.</p><h2 id="The-nature-of-surprise"><a href="#The-nature-of-surprise" class="headerlink" title="The nature of surprise"></a>The nature of surprise</h2><p>People have evolved with the sense of surprise. It has helped us survive in a changing environment by making us more alert to things that don’t go exactly how we expect. When surprised, someone might flee or just get really alert to the situation. So maybe this phenomenon can be used to stimulate people to learn more about bitcoin, or money in general.</p><p>There are many surprising aspects with fiat money. In particular, people assume a lot of things that are not true with the USD or EUR but are true with bitcoin.</p><h2 id="Surprising-questions"><a href="#Surprising-questions" class="headerlink" title="Surprising questions"></a>Surprising questions</h2><p>Certain facts about money and banks have always circulated around as trivia. But maybe they are quire important and it’s possible to make simple questions, based on them, that are extremely surprising for many people. The typical ones that occur to me are bellow.</p><h3 id="Did-you-know-that-the-money-in-your-wallet-is-not-really-yours"><a href="#Did-you-know-that-the-money-in-your-wallet-is-not-really-yours" class="headerlink" title="Did you know that the money in your wallet is not really yours?"></a>Did you know that the money in your wallet is not really yours?</h3><p>If it was really your property there would not be <a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/uscode/text/18/333">legislation making it illegal to destroy it</a> or the need to distinguish money from other property in laws regarding theft. All bills and coins are government property and the destruction of all government property, by citizens, is typically illegal. This means the government is extremely gracious to let us all use their money for our daily affairs.</p><h3 id="Did-you-know-that-your-bank-does-not-need-to-give-you-back-the-money-in-your-savings-account"><a href="#Did-you-know-that-your-bank-does-not-need-to-give-you-back-the-money-in-your-savings-account" class="headerlink" title="Did you know that your bank does not need to give you back the money in your savings account?"></a>Did you know that your bank does not need to give you back the money in your savings account?</h3><p>Queue South Parks’ <a href="https://youtu.be/TGwZVGKG30s">“And it’s GONE!” scene</a>.</p><p>The money was not yours to start with. When you deposit 1000 into a bank account you give the money to the bank and become a creditor. Everything goes well until the bank goes bankrupt which means it can’t pay what it owes you. You can’t demand your money back because it’s not your money so you have to get in line with all the other creditors.</p><p>If you’re European you may have heard of the <a href="https://ec.europa.eu/info/business-economy-euro/banking-and-finance/banking-union/european-deposit-insurance-scheme_en">deposit insurance scheme</a> that guarantees deposits up to €100,000. If it was really your money there would be no need for that insurance.</p><h3 id="Did-you-know-that-your-1000-deposit-can-buy-10-000-of-goods"><a href="#Did-you-know-that-your-1000-deposit-can-buy-10-000-of-goods" class="headerlink" title="Did you know that your 1000 deposit can buy 10,000 of goods?"></a>Did you know that your 1000 deposit can buy 10,000 of goods?</h3><p>It’s magic! Actually it’s <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fractional-reserve_banking">fractional reserve banking</a> but it could as well be magic because money is made out of thin air.</p><p>Banks are only required to keep a fraction – like 10% – of the money people deposit. The rest they can give to other people in loans. From your 1000 deposit the bank can give a loan of 900 to another person. That person can take those 900 and make a new deposit, the new deposit be used to create a new loan of 810, and so on. At the end of it, if everyone withdrew the deposited money, there would be 10,000 available. This is an exaggeration of what happens in reality but it happens.</p><h2 id="Do-you-know-more"><a href="#Do-you-know-more" class="headerlink" title="Do you know more?"></a>Do you know more?</h2><p>These are the most basic ones. Many people will not act on them. Some people might just want to disprove these things and go search for it. Others might feel they are less safe than they thought and go search for solutions. All of those are a good outcome, in my book.</p><p>What do you think? Can these kind of questions stimulate people to be more curious about the absolute insanities of some parts of the financial system? Do you know other questions that spark the same sense of surprise? Tell about it in the comments.</p>]]></content>
    
    
      
      
    <summary type="html">&lt;img src=&quot;/posts/2019/03/06/surprise-heres-bitcoin/surprise-heres-bitcoin.jpg&quot; class=&quot;&quot;&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been wondering about a more effective way </summary>
      
    
    
    
    <category term="ideas" scheme="http://m4ktub.ws/categories/ideas/"/>
    
    
    <category term="bitcoin" scheme="http://m4ktub.ws/tags/bitcoin/"/>
    
    <category term="communication" scheme="http://m4ktub.ws/tags/communication/"/>
    
    <category term="surprise" scheme="http://m4ktub.ws/tags/surprise/"/>
    
    <category term="human nature" scheme="http://m4ktub.ws/tags/human-nature/"/>
    
    <category term="finance" scheme="http://m4ktub.ws/tags/finance/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Privacy: Your Consent Is Not Needed</title>
    <link href="http://m4ktub.ws/posts/2019/02/22/privacy-your-consent-is-not-needed/"/>
    <id>http://m4ktub.ws/posts/2019/02/22/privacy-your-consent-is-not-needed/</id>
    <published>2019-02-22T00:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2019-11-13T12:14:29.399Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Some time ago I’ve read that privacy is a matter of consent.</p><blockquote><p>privacy is about consent</p><footer><strong>someone</strong><cite>the internet</cite></footer></blockquote><p>It made me think. Yeah, it makes sense. If you don’t give your consent to share certain information, and someone does it, then that’s a violation of your privacy. And most services ask your consent, through privacy policies or the service’s terms and agreements, which seem to recognize that privacy is about consent.</p><p>But that wasn’t the end of that wandering thought. Something was missing. Consent certainly covers part of it because when you give your consent your already acknowledge that privacy leak. But it doesn’t seem general enough as, in my opinion, privacy is a matter of controlling information.</p><h2 id="Information-technology"><a href="#Information-technology" class="headerlink" title="Information technology"></a>Information technology</h2><img src="/posts/2019/02/22/privacy-your-consent-is-not-needed/google-dictionary-trends.png" class=""><p>Technology made the world a smaller place by making global travel accessible and global communication commonplace. On the one side, we’re able to talk with anyone almost anywhere in the world. On the other hand, that comes with the realization that technology, specially communication technology, makes us more exposed.</p><p>We form a crude mental picture of how computers, phones, the Internet works and move on with our business. Until we’re suprised by a leak. As always, surprise is there to guide us through the world. We leak information in everything we do and our sense of privacy can be violated in the most surprising ways. Big Brother, for example, <a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/kashmirhill/2012/02/16/how-target-figured-out-a-teen-girl-was-pregnant-before-her-father-did/#8d940c266686">knows when a woman is pregnant, just from leaked information</a>, weeks before her friends.</p><h2 id="The-ability-to-conceal"><a href="#The-ability-to-conceal" class="headerlink" title="The ability to conceal"></a>The ability to conceal</h2><p>So I think privacy is mostly about the ability to conceal information from observers. Information truly wants to be free and our ability to keep information private is compromised at the very moment it is produced. Once produced, it can be captured, reproduced, and made public. So, in general, consent is meaningless. We actually depend a lot on others to keep our privacy because we lack the ability to stop them. We may use “consent” as our desire to retain the ability to prevent leaks, but we actually cannot stop a secret from being retold.</p><p>Even if we create barriers to mark our private sphere, as we always do, it always has breaches, specially in the age of information. Our lack of understanding about how things work and lack of ability to conceal private matters is what creates this sense of exposure.</p><h2 id="Expectations"><a href="#Expectations" class="headerlink" title="Expectations"></a>Expectations</h2><p>With changing technology there’s always a gap between what we think we are able to conceal and what we are actually able to conceal. We also cannot tell for sure if some aspect of our private lives was captured until it’s public. And in many situations we depend on others to protect our privacy. So essentially, the violation of our privacy is a matter of expectations. Consent is just playing nice.</p><blockquote><p>privacy is about expectations</p><footer><strong>m4ktub</strong><cite>the internet (misattributed)</cite></footer></blockquote><p>We create a model of how the world works and expect that to be true. Any deviation generates surprise and makes us alert to that new reality. We would like the ability to stop everything from leaking, but we actually don’t. We would like to be asked for consent for most things that affect us, but we actually aren’t.</p><p>We can’t unshare things. So, instead, we must learn what information we leak and either improve our ability to control that or adjust our expectations. Both those things are important and productive. Demanding consent to be asked works but is unreliable.</p><p>At some time in the future our thoughts, the last bastion of privacy, will be at stake. Some technology will be able to sense our most intimate ideas at a distance. In this arms race, if we don’t improve our understanding and ability to control privacy we must adjust our expectations of freedom.</p><blockquote><p>without privacy there can be no freedom</p><footer><strong>reasonable people</strong><cite>everywhere</cite></footer></blockquote>]]></content>
    
    
      
      
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Some time ago I’ve read that privacy is a matter of consent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;privacy is about consent&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;footer&gt;&lt;strong&gt;someone&lt;/str</summary>
      
    
    
    
    <category term="ideas" scheme="http://m4ktub.ws/categories/ideas/"/>
    
    
    <category term="privacy" scheme="http://m4ktub.ws/tags/privacy/"/>
    
    <category term="expectations" scheme="http://m4ktub.ws/tags/expectations/"/>
    
    <category term="consent" scheme="http://m4ktub.ws/tags/consent/"/>
    
    <category term="technology" scheme="http://m4ktub.ws/tags/technology/"/>
    
    <category term="futurology" scheme="http://m4ktub.ws/tags/futurology/"/>
    
    <category term="brainstorm" scheme="http://m4ktub.ws/tags/brainstorm/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>The expectations around CashAddr</title>
    <link href="http://m4ktub.ws/posts/2019/02/04/the-expectations-around-cashaddr/"/>
    <id>http://m4ktub.ws/posts/2019/02/04/the-expectations-around-cashaddr/</id>
    <published>2019-02-04T00:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2019-11-13T12:14:29.397Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<img src="/posts/2019/02/04/the-expectations-around-cashaddr/cashaddr.png" class=""><p>When <a href="https://www.bitcoinabc.org/2018-01-14-CashAddr/">CashAddr</a> was introduced, my expectation for that address format was that it would replace the legacy Base58Check encoding in all its uses. The same way Bitcoin historically had addresses starting with 1 and 3, Bitcoin Cash would have addresses starting with q and p.</p><p>From early on, it was obvious that most of the ecosystem had adopted CashAddr for standard addresses but had preserved support for legacy addresses and, in particular, continued to use the legacy encoding in paper wallets, for example. My rationalization for that was that the effort was probably not worth it, but never have I questioned the ability to use CashAddr in those cases.</p><p>Recently when Cash Accounts was announced, a lot of excitement was generated around it. In particular, I was excited with the possibility that wallets, like Copay, could support Cash Accounts together with stealth addresses or payment codes. It was obvious that any such address would be a CashAddr like “bitcoincash:something” or, at least, “stealth:somethingelse”. You would be able to scan those directly or just type Cash Accounts, which would be a simple way of achieving the same.</p><p>But the expectations I had for CashAddr started to be broken when Jonathan Silverblood <a href="https://twitter.com/monsterbitar/status/1078931367994494976">mentioned CashAddr could not encode a payment code</a>, that is, that it could not be used to represent those addresses. When I looked at the specification, with more detail, I finally realized that it had been defined in a very specific way that was not really reusable.</p><p>The last thing I wanted was another Copay address like Csomethingagain so I started a <a href="https://github.com/bitcoincashorg/bitcoincash.org/pull/259">revision of the specification</a>. After reading it, it seemed there was a simple way to make it more general and, at the same time, make it clearer how it could be used to encode anything we could perceive as addresses.</p><p>But by trying to review the specification I’ve also found that not only it had been defined in a non-reusable way but it also had been done so on purpose as <a href="https://twitter.com/m4ktub2/status/1085934444509384709">the intended use was different than what I expected</a>. Boom! Minder shattered.</p><p>The idea is that “bitcoincash:…” addresses only represent the direct forms of payment that we know and that all other payment use cases should use a different prefix. Taking a step back and letting go of my previous approach, I can see the logic. It would be ok to have something like stealth… or paymentcode:… but the specification was ambiguous and inconsistent which actually made it impossible to interpret it that way. So I did <a href="https://github.com/bitcoincashorg/bitcoincash.org/pull/266">another revision</a> with that approach in mind…</p><p>The goal with all this is to have a well defined specification that is reusable for all sort of addresses. Ideally the revision would be a version 1.1, that is, a minor change that keeps everything compatible but that’s not quite possible due to how version 1.0 was written. Luckily, practice does not match theory. Most libraries implement CashAddr in a very narrow way. On the one hand, those libraries don’t implement the specification correctly. On the other hand, that possibly allows a version 1.1 (or 2.0, if we want to be correct with the semantics) to be made since those libraries would not be affected in practice. Nothing that is working would fail, the libraries would just be broken in a different way, which is curious… at least to me.</p>]]></content>
    
    
      
      
    <summary type="html">&lt;img src=&quot;/posts/2019/02/04/the-expectations-around-cashaddr/cashaddr.png&quot; class=&quot;&quot;&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bitcoinabc.org/2018-01-14</summary>
      
    
    
    
    <category term="projects" scheme="http://m4ktub.ws/categories/projects/"/>
    
    
    <category term="cashaddr" scheme="http://m4ktub.ws/tags/cashaddr/"/>
    
    <category term="specification" scheme="http://m4ktub.ws/tags/specification/"/>
    
    <category term="expectations" scheme="http://m4ktub.ws/tags/expectations/"/>
    
    <category term="cashaccounts" scheme="http://m4ktub.ws/tags/cashaccounts/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Ownership vs possession</title>
    <link href="http://m4ktub.ws/posts/2019/01/19/ownership-vs-possession/"/>
    <id>http://m4ktub.ws/posts/2019/01/19/ownership-vs-possession/</id>
    <published>2019-01-19T00:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2020-04-02T01:00:00.000Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A few weeks ago I came across the following Tweet:</p><img src="/posts/2019/01/19/ownership-vs-possession/tweet-01.png" class="" title="https:&#x2F;&#x2F;twitter.com&#x2F;dgenr818&#x2F;status&#x2F;1080847974404579329"><p>TDIL (That Day I Learned) that even the most knowledgeable can be defenseless against perceived authority as they shut down critical thinking.</p><p>Everyone should know that the law distinguishes possession from ownership. That’s what allows safe deposit boxes to exist or makes theft a crime. I also agree that unintentional possession can be a problem in some circumstances. I certainly don’t want drugs put in my backpack, without my knowledge, when I’m travelling!</p><p>But let’s consider the example where someone offers you a $100 bill. If you don’t know the person you may want to reject it because you don’t want to be exposed to whatever comes attached to that offer. (That would be a useful feature for <a href="https://cointext.io/">CoinText</a>, for example. When you send Bitcoin Cash to a new number, that number could first receive a message asking for consent, before actually doing the transfer.) But if you’re face to face, and accept the money, it’s hard to argue that you don’t intend to receive it.</p><p>So let’s change the situation! Imagine you put $1 in an envelope and into someone else’s mailbox. (It’s your money now, so we’ll use less. Even imaginary money is hard to give away.) Would you say that that person cannot spend the money? Would you say that you didn’t intend to give that money or, in other terms, transfer the ownership of that money? I would guess not.</p><p>Bitcoin Cash works like that and even makes intent clearer. Contrary to intuition, when you give someone your address and that person sends you Bitcoin Cash it’s the other person that stipulates how you can spend that money. Attached to the transaction is a contract, in Bitcoin script, that basically says “the only person that can spend this coins is the owner of the key for this address”. So, whenever someone sends you Bitcoin Cash, they are voluntarily writing a contract that gives you ownership of the coins and signing it. It’s a bit hard to argue, after that, that the person didn’t intend to send you the coins or that you can’t spend them. The only thing you need to convert that possession to ownership is have the intent to own them. Do you want money? There! It’s yours.</p><p>If Bitcoin Cash was perfectly fungible, that is, if no one could know where did the coins come from, then no one would worry about these things. But coins can be tracked and sending someone a small amount, just to then track their expenses, is a real possibility. People can look for these cases (some actually do) and donate those coins to miners. It’s the equivalent of receiving money in your mailbox and handing it over to the police. The price of a little more privacy…</p><p>Obviously laws are different everywhere. Apparently <a href="http://www.dumblaws.com/laws/united-states/alaska">moose cannot be thrown from a plane</a> and I’ve heard from someone that some dictator or emperor ordered the Sun to rise at a certain time. It’s possible to put anything into law. But let’s be real and be critical. Laws are always behind the times and some things just don’t make sense.</p><p>__<br>Disclaimer: this post was written very high on <a href="https://www.smbc-comics.com/index.php?db=comics&id=2475#comic">mount stupid</a>.</p>]]></content>
    
    
      
      
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A few weeks ago I came across the following Tweet:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/posts/2019/01/19/ownership-vs-possession/tweet-01.png&quot; class=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;</summary>
      
    
    
    
    <category term="opinions" scheme="http://m4ktub.ws/categories/opinions/"/>
    
    
    <category term="bitcoin" scheme="http://m4ktub.ws/tags/bitcoin/"/>
    
    <category term="coins" scheme="http://m4ktub.ws/tags/coins/"/>
    
    <category term="ownership" scheme="http://m4ktub.ws/tags/ownership/"/>
    
    <category term="possession" scheme="http://m4ktub.ws/tags/possession/"/>
    
    <category term="interpretation" scheme="http://m4ktub.ws/tags/interpretation/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
</feed>
